I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we do the math on how many
fewer calories we have to eat every day
to lose one pound of body fat.
The first surgical attempt at
body sculpting was in 1921,
with a dancer wanting to improve
the shape of her ankles.
The surgeon apparently
scraped away too much tissue
and tied the stitches too tight,
resulting in necrosis, amputation,
and the first recorded malpractice
suit in the history of plastic surgery.
Today's liposuction is much safer—
only killing about 1 in 5,000 patients,
mostly from unknown causes—
throwing a clot off into your lung,
or perforations of
your internal organs.
Liposuction currently reigns as
the most popular cosmetic surgery
in the world, and its effects
are indeed, only cosmetic.
A study published in the New
England Journal of Medicine
assessed obese women before and
after having about 20 pounds of fat
sucked out of their bodies,
resulting in nearly a 20%
drop in their total body fat.
Normally, lose even just 5-10%
of your body weight in fat,
and you get significant improvements
in blood pressure, blood sugars,
inflammation, cholesterol,
and triglycerides,
but liposuction sucks: none
of those benefits materialized
even after the massive liposuction.
This suggests subcutaneous fat, the
fat under our skin, is not the problem.
The metabolic insults of obesity
arise from the visceral fat,
the fat surrounding or even
infiltrating our internal organs
like the fat marbling
our muscles and liver.
The way you lose that fat,
the dangerous fat,
is to take in fewer
calories than you burn.
Anyone who's seen The Biggest
Loser shows knows with enough
calorie restriction and exercise
hundreds of pounds can be lost.
Similarly, there are cases in the medical
literature of what some refer to as
"super obesity" in which individuals
lost up to 374 pounds, largely
on their own without professional
help and kept it off for years.
The guy lost about 20 pounds
a month cycling two hours a day
and reducing intake to 800 calories
a day, which is down around
what some prisoners were getting at
concentration camps in World War II.
Perhaps America's most
celebrated TV weight loss
was when Oprah pulled
out a wagon full of fat,
representing the 67 pounds she
lost on a very-low-calorie diet.
How many calories did she have to
cut to achieve that within four months?
Consult leading nutrition textbooks,
or refer to trusted authorities
like the Mayo Clinic, and you'll
learn the simple weight loss rule: one
pound of fat is equal to 3,500 calories.
Quoting from the Journal of the
American Medical Association:
A total of 3500 calories
equals 1 pound of body weight.
This means if you decrease your
intake by 500 calories daily,
you will lose 1 pound per
week. 500 calories per day
x 7 days = 3500 calories,
so 1 pound of body fat.
The simple weight loss
rule that's simply not true.
The 3,500-calorie rule can be
traced back to a paper in 1958
that just noted that since fatty tissue
on the human body is 87% fat,
a pound of body fat would have
about 395 grams of pure fat.
Multiply that by nine calories
per gram of fat gives you that
3,500 calories per
pound approximation.
The fatal flaw that leads to
dramatically exaggerated
weight loss predictions
is that the 3,500 rule fails
to take into account the fact
that changes in the Calories-In
side of the energy-balance
equation automatically lead to
changes in Calories Out,
for example the slowing
of metabolic rate that
accompanies weight loss
known as metabolic adaptation.
That's one of the reasons
weight loss plateaus.
For example, imagine a 30-year-old
sedentary woman of average height
who weighs 150 pounds.
According to the 3,500-calorie rule,
if she cuts 500 calories out of her
daily diet, she'd lose a pound a week,
or 52 pounds a year. In three
years then, she would vanish.
She'd go from 150 pounds to negative 6.
Obviously, that doesn't happen.
What would happen is that in the first
year instead of losing 52 pounds,
she'd likely only lose 32 pounds
and then, after a total of three years,
stabilize at about 100 pounds.
This is because it takes fewer
calories to exist as a thin person.
Part of it is simple mechanics,
in the same way a Hummer requires
more fuel than a compact car---
think how much more effort it
would take to just get out of a chair,
walk across the room, or climb a few
stairs carrying a 50-pound backpack.
That's no lighter than carrying
50 pounds in the front.
Even when you're lying
at rest, sound asleep,
there's simply less of your body
to maintain as we lose weight.
Every pound of fat tissue lost may
mean one less mile of blood vessels
your body has to pump
blood through every minute.
So the basic upkeep and movement
of thinner bodies takes fewer calories.
So as you lose weight by eating
less, you end up needing less.
That's what the 3,500-calorie
rule doesn't take into account.
Or imagine it the other way.
A 200-pound man starts eating
500 more calories a day.
That's like a large soda
or two doughnuts.
According to the 3,500-calories
rule, in 10 years he'd weigh
more than 700 pounds!
That doesn't happen
because the heavier he is,
the more calories he
burns just existing.
If you're a hundred pounds overweight,
that's like the skinny person inside you
trying to walk around balancing
13 gallons of oil at all times,
or lugging around a sack containing
400 sticks of butter wherever you go.
It takes about two doughnuts worth of
extra energy just to live at 250 pounds,
and so that's where he'd
plateau out if he kept it up.
So weight gain or weight loss, given
a certain calorie excess or deficit,
is a curve that flattens out over time
rather than a straight line up or down.
Nevertheless, the 3500-calorie
rule continues to crop up,
even in obesity journals.
Public health researchers used it
to calculate how many pounds
children might lose every year if,
for example, fast food kid's meals
swapped in apple slices
instead of French fries.
They figured two meals a week could
add up to about four pounds a year.
The actual difference—National
Restaurant Association-funded
researchers were no doubt
delighted to point out—
would probably add less
than half a pound,10 times
less than the 3500-calorie
rule would predict.
The original article was
subsequently retracted.
In our next story,
we try to understand the metabolic
and behavioral adaptations
that slow weight loss.
We have millions of years of evolution
hard-wiring us to survive scarcity,
compensatory survival mechanisms our
body uses to defend against weight loss.
So when we start losing weight, we
may unconsciously start moving less
as a behavioral adaptation
to conserve energy.
There are metabolic adaptations as
well. Our metabolism slows down.
Every pound of weight loss may
reduce our resting metabolic rate
by seven calories a day. This may only
translate to a few percent differences
for most, but can rapidly snowball for
those who achieve massive weight loss.
During one session, some of
The Biggest Loser contestants
famously had their
metabolic rates tracked.
Above and beyond the hundreds of
calories less it takes to just exist
100+ pounds lighter, by the end of
the season their metabolic rates
slowed by an extra
500 calories a day.
The mindblower was that six
years later they were retested
and still had the 500-calorie-a-day
handicap. So the contestants had to cut
500 calories more than anyone else their
size to maintain the same weight loss.
No wonder the bulk of
their weight was regained.
Most remained at least 10% lower
than their starting weight, though,
and even a 7% drop has been shown
to cut diabetes rates about in half.
Still, the metabolic slowing means
you have to work that much harder
than everyone else
just to stay in place.
Analyzing four seasons of The
Biggest Loser, minute-by-minute,
researchers noted that 85% of the
focus was on exercise rather than diet,
though the exercise component accounted
for less than half of the weight loss.
Even six years after their season ended,
the contestants had been maintaining
an hour of daily, vigorous exercise,
yet still regained most of the weight.
Why? Because they
started eating more.
They could have
cut their exercise
to just 20 minutes a
day and still maintained
100% of their initial weight
loss if they would have just
been able to keep their intake
to under 3,000 calories a day.
That may not sound like
much of a challenge,
but weight loss doesn't just slow your
metabolism; it boosts your appetite.
If it were just a matter of your weight
settling at the point at which
your reduced calorie intake matches
your reduced calorie output,
it would take years for your
weight loss to plateau.
Instead, it often happens
within six to eight months.
You may know the drill:
Start the diet, stick to the diet,
and then weight loss stalls
six months later.
What happened?
Don't blame your metabolism;
that just plays a small part.
What happened is that you likely
actually stopped sticking to your diet
because your appetite went on
a rampage. Let's break it down.
If you cut 800 calories
out of your daily diet—
2600 calories a day
down to 1800—
and your weight loss stalls after six
months, then what happened is
that at the end of the first month you
think you're still cutting 800 calories,
but you may actually only be
down about 600 calories a day.
By month two you're
only down about 500,
month three, 300, and by month
six you're only eating 200 calories
less than before
you went on the diet.
In other words, you inadvertently
suffered an exponential increase
in calorie intake over
those six months.
Yet you may not even realize
it, because by that time
your body may have ramped
your appetite up 600 calories.
So, it still feels as if you are
eating 800 calories less,
but it's actually only 200.
Since an 800 calorie drop in
intake may slow your metabolism
and physical activity
about 200 calories a day,
with no difference between Calories In
and Calories Out at six months,
no wonder your weight loss
grinds to a complete halt.
The slow upward drift in
calorie intake on a new diet
is not because you got lazy.
Once your appetite is boosted by
600 calories after dieting for a while,
eating 200 calories less at the end
is as hard as eating 800 calories
less at the beginning.
So you can maintain the same
disciplined level of willpower
and self-control and still
end up stagnating.
To prevent this from happening, you
need to maintain the calorie deficit.
How is that possible in the
face of a ravenous appetite?
Hunger is a biological drive.
Asking someone to eat
smaller portions
is like asking someone
to take fewer breaths.
You can white-knuckle it for a bit,
but eventually nature wins out.
That's why I wrote
How Not to Diet.
There are foods that can counter
the slowing of our metabolism
and suppress our appetite,
ways of eating to counter
the behavioral adaptation
and even eat more food
yet still lose weight.
Due to the metabolic slowing
and increased appetite
that accompanies weight loss,
sustained weight loss requires
a persistent calorie deficit
of 300 to 500 calories a day.
This can be accomplished
without reducing portion sizes
simply by lowering the
calorie density of meals.
This can result in the rare
combination of weight loss
with both an increase in quality and
even quantity of food consumed.
The bottom line is that
sustainable weight loss
is not about eating less food;
it's about eating better food.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.